<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A French conquest neither desirable nor practicable dedicated to the King of England.</title>
            <author>Lawton, Charlwood, 1660-1721.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49823</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L739</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20684</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12403862</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12403862</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61333</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49823)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61333)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 281:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A French conquest neither desirable nor practicable dedicated to the King of England.</title>
                  <author>Lawton, Charlwood, 1660-1721.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by His Majesty's servants,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Charlwood Lawton. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Two columns to the page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61333:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61333:1"/>
            <p>A <hi>French Conqueſt</hi> NEITHER DESIRABLE NOR PRACTICABLE.</p>
            <p>DEDICATED TO THE KING of ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed by His MAJESTY's Servants. MDCXCIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:61333:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61333:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NOtwithſtanding <hi>You</hi> have been traduced by Your Enemies for having ill Deſigns upon the <hi>Nation,</hi> and that theſe Enemies have had too fatal a Succeſs in ſpreading ſuch improbable Suggeſtions (too fatal for their <hi>Native Country</hi> as well as for <hi>You,</hi> who are the <hi>Monarch</hi> of it;) yet I am ſo aſſur'd that Your <hi>Majeſty</hi> jealously watches over the <hi>Glory,</hi> and Aims at the <hi>True Intereſt</hi> of Your <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> that I am confident a Diſcourſe that proves a <hi>French Conqueſt</hi> of this <hi>Iſland,</hi> to be neither the <hi>Intention</hi> of Your <hi>Friends,</hi> nor <hi>Your Own,</hi> nor <hi>Practicable</hi> in it ſelf, will not be an unacceptable Preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CONQUEST</hi> is a harſh Word, and it frightens weak Minds. And that <hi>YOU Your Self</hi> ſhould <hi>Conquer,</hi> can be only wiſh'd for by ſuch, as intend <hi>their own Intereſt</hi> more than <hi>Yours,</hi> in Your <hi>Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> who intend to live upon <hi>Prey,</hi> and would deſtroy half the <hi>Nation</hi> that <hi>They</hi> might have the better ſhare of the <hi>Confiſcations.</hi> But if that ſhould be, yet the moſt remote ſurviving <hi>Relations</hi> of thoſe that are <hi>Killed,</hi> or <hi>Executed,</hi> when that <hi>horrid Trial of Skill</hi> ſhall be over, will have a mind to the Eſtates of their <hi>Anceſtors:</hi> And the Baniſhed <hi>Out-Laws</hi> will be ready to ſtir up any <hi>enterprizing Prince abroad,</hi> or ſuch as are diſcontented at <hi>home,</hi> to give future Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances; So that theſe <hi>Kingdoms</hi> will be ſtill continued under <hi>Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Agonies.</hi> And, after all, I beg leave to ſay, That no <hi>Prince</hi> by <hi>Conquering,</hi> or, to ſpeak more properly, <hi>Reducing,</hi> his <hi>Rebellious Subjects,</hi> can have any <hi>Title</hi> to take away the <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of thoſe that remained Faithful.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:61333:3"/>
            <p>I must confeſs, I am one of thoſe that can never (as well for His, as Our ſake) aſſiſt any <hi>King</hi> that has the <hi>Glorious Title of SUCCES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SION,</hi> to debaſe it into the <hi>mean, hated,</hi> and <hi>precarious one</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</hi> But I think our own <hi>Hereditary</hi> and <hi>Equal Monarchy</hi> to be ſo much the moſt happy ſort of <hi>Government,</hi> both for <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> that I can very willingly run any hazard to ſettle things upon <hi>that Foundation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come Home, Great Sir,</hi> to Reſtore our <hi>Trade,</hi> to Repair our <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val Reputation</hi> and <hi>Strength,</hi> to make <hi>Us</hi> the <hi>Umpires</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> to Deliver <hi>Us</hi> from <hi>Dutch</hi> Deluſions to Preſerve Our <hi>Church</hi> as Eſtabliſhed by <hi>Law</hi> from being <hi>Debauched</hi> by <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> to Settle <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> in a <hi>duly Elected PARLIAMENT,</hi> and to Eſtabliſh all the <hi>Liberties</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subject.</p>
            <p>It is becauſe I am confident theſe are Your <hi>Royal Reſolutions,</hi> that I Wrote this ſhort Diſcourſe, and now Dedicate it to <hi>Your Majeſty.</hi> The Subject is of that Importance to <hi>Your Affairs,</hi> that it deſerved to have been better handled; and I deſired ſome other Pens to have undertaken it, but <hi>Their</hi> Thoughts were otherwiſe employed: Yet though I am ſenſible I have not done it all the Juſtice <hi>They</hi> would, I think I may without Vanity ſay, I have made it plain beyond the <hi>Cavils,</hi> or at least reaſonable <hi>Objections,</hi> of Your <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> and I hope it may have ſome effect upon <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That God would Reſtore <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> to Your <hi>Throne,</hi> and to the <hi>Hearts</hi> of all Your <hi>Subjects,</hi> is the unfeigned Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your <hi>Majeſty,</hi>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Majeſty<hi>'s moſt Obedient, Loyal Subject, N. N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61333:3"/>
            <head>A <hi>French Conqueſt</hi> NEITHER Deſirable nor Practicable.</head>
            <p>SINCE our Enemies, in ſome of their <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> and many of their <hi>Diſcourſes,</hi> amongſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other things wherewith they falſly charge thoſe whoſe <hi>ſole</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is to reſtore the <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Monarchy,</hi> together with all thoſe Securities we ever had, or are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the Preſervation of the <hi>Engliſh Liberties</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> I ſay, Since our Enemies, amongſt other things, unjuſtly charge us with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning, or, at leaſt, unwarily helping forward, a <hi>French Conqueſt,</hi> I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to ſhew that ſuch a <hi>Conqueſt</hi> is neither <hi>Deſirable</hi> nor <hi>Practicable;</hi> that we are neither ſuch <hi>Fools</hi> nor <hi>Knaves</hi> as to think of ſuch fatal Projects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our <hi>Native Country.</hi> I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make out both the One and the Other plainly, but not elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, ſince Brevity and Perſpicuity is more proper to diſabuſe the honeſt and plain-hearted (for whoſe Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation I particularly write, and who are moſt miſled by theſe Inſinuations) than long and artificial Harrangues, wherein the Authors refine too much, or interlard too much Learning.</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt Head of my Diſcourſe, <hi>viz. That a</hi> French Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt <hi>is not deſirable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no ſort of Men deſire it. I know no body that would ſubject our <hi>Fortunes,</hi> our <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> to the Power of <hi>France:</hi> They that urge it, don't believe we would. We lament the <hi>Taxes,</hi> the <hi>Impriſonments,</hi> the <hi>Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings,</hi> and the Pillaging of <hi>England;</hi> the <hi>Torturing</hi> againſt Law, and the <hi>Glenco-Maſſacre</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all the other Miſeries that infeſt this <hi>Iſland;</hi> We would not bring more upon it; we would not depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulate it; we would not make it a <hi>Golgetha:</hi> And that the World may be convinced that none of the <hi>Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites</hi> deſire a <hi>French Conqueſt,</hi> I ſhall ſhew it contrary to the <hi>Intereſts</hi> and <hi>Inclinations</hi> of every Denomination of them to let the <hi>French</hi> have any foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here.</p>
            <p>It is almoſt a Jeſt to go about to prove the <hi>Whiggiſh Jacchites</hi> would not find their Account in a <hi>French Conqueſt.</hi> Can it be imagined, that Men who have been always ſtruggling with their <hi>own</hi> Kings for <hi>more Liberty,</hi> and to have their <hi>Properties</hi> better guarded, who have been hitherto ſo jealous of the loweſt Imitations of <hi>French Monarchy,</hi> ſhould expect greater Securities un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>Provincial <hi>French Government,</hi>
               </hi> or deſire to become Subjects to a <hi>King</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:61333:4"/>whoſe own <hi>Natural Subjects</hi> they think are very hardly dealt with?</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Jacobites</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nothing can lie more croſs to their Notions and Intereſt, than a <hi>French Conqueſt.</hi> Can it be believed that thoſe who venture <hi>All</hi> to preſerve every Gradation of the <hi>Royal Line,</hi> would convey over the Tenure of the Crown to one that has <hi>no</hi> Pretence of Right to it? Did they not oppoſe the <hi>Bill of Excluſion</hi> upon this Principle, That it is not in the Power of <hi>King and Parliament</hi> too to alter the <hi>Succeſſion?</hi> Can they then give up the Intereſt of our <hi>Engliſh Monarchs</hi> all at once? No, their Conſciences will bid them oppoſe a <hi>French Conqueſt</hi> with the hazard and expence of the laſt Drop of their Blood: And their Intereſt will bid them do ſo too; for a <hi>French Conqueſt</hi> cannot be maintained here without ſo many <hi>Outlandiſh Roman Catholicks,</hi> as will be a very <hi>indifferent Guard</hi> to the <hi>Church of England;</hi> and if the <hi>French King</hi> ſhould be King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> he muſt in meer Policy ſet up his own Religion here, if he did not think himſelf obliged in Conſcience to do it.</p>
            <p>I come in the laſt place to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks,</hi> (of whom our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries expect the World ſhould believe any Figment, tho' never ſo monſtrous and abſurd;) and I muſt ſay, That thoſe among them who, by reaſon of their Eſtates and Sence, will always govern the reſt, are not ſo little read in our <hi>Hiſtories,</hi> as to ſuppoſe, that, tho' ſuch a <hi>Conqueſt</hi> did at preſent make for them, (as it really will not) it would be laſting. They are now convinced, that it is by becoming <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> and not by running coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Engliſh Intereſt,</hi> that they muſt be happy; and they profeſs, that if we will once give them oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to ſhew how well they love our <hi>Liberties,</hi> we ſhall ſee they place their Hopes in the <hi>Indulgence,</hi> they ſhall gain by the moderate and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive Carriage of their own <hi>Party,</hi> and not on <hi>Foreign Dependencies.</hi> They know that the Revulſe of all ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects muſt extirpate <hi>Them</hi> and their <hi>Poſterity</hi> together with the <hi>Foreigners;</hi> and they know we muſt be entirely rooted out, or we ſhall root out all Foreigners at laſt.</p>
            <p>I muſt do that <hi>Party</hi> ſtill more Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. I thought always they were neither Wiſely nor Religiouſly uſed by us; that we ought not to puniſh any Man for meer Opinions, and that we ought not in good Senſe to irritate Men into <hi>Treaſons</hi> at <hi>Home,</hi> or <hi>Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies</hi> on <hi>Foreign Princes:</hi> This I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways thought; but ſince the Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of <hi>His Majeſty</hi> I have had Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to converſe more freely with the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and I muſt ſay, I have found amongſt many of that Perſuaſion the ſame Senſe of <hi>Liberty</hi> their <hi>Anceſtors</hi> had, and our <hi>Old Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> who have tranſmitted to us our <hi>Magna Charta, Charta de Forreſta,</hi> &amp;c. I have found amongſt ſo many of that Perſuaſion not only all the good Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of that Happineſs we enjoy by our <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> but ſo particular a Deteſtation of all Thoughts of a <hi>French Conqueſt,</hi> that as I think no Death too cruel for any body that would promote it, ſo I am confident whoever can be proved deſigning it, would be found Guilty even by any <hi>Jury of Papiſts</hi> that can be ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61333:4"/>
            <p>There are poſſibly ſome <hi>Rom. Prieſts,</hi> that may endeavour to blow up the <hi>Laity</hi> to ſome unreaſonable Hopes and Deſigns; but I am well ſatisfied a <hi>French Conqueſt</hi> is none of them, and beſides the <hi>Laity</hi> of that <hi>Church</hi> begin to reflect upon the Folly of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> when the <hi>King</hi> was here; and they now ſee, that the <hi>Prieſts</hi> are <hi>light</hi> Gentlemen <hi>without Families or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes,</hi> and ſo can better ſhift in a Storm than the Laity can, which makes <hi>Ghoſtly Politicks</hi> much out of faſhion even with the <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,</hi> that have Senſe, Quality and Eſtates; and they will always go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the reſt, in what concerns the ſecurity of their Perſons and Eſtates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cambden,</hi> though in many reſpects an excellent Hiſtorian, whether out of Bigotry to his own Church, or that he may enhaunce the Character of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who made and promoted ſuch ſevere Laws againſt both, never ſpeaks favourably either of <hi>Puritan</hi> or <hi>Papist,</hi> and yet there drop from him Expreſſions, which ſhew, although the <hi>Reformation</hi> was then ſo newly ſetled, and though the <hi>Papiſts</hi> were then more numerous than they are now; nay, though they were not many of them ſatisfied of the Legitimacy of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> yet the generallity, and the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Papiſts would not joyn in the <hi>Spaniſh Deſigns;</hi> and they blamed the hot-headedneſs of <hi>Parſons</hi> the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Read <hi>Cambden</hi>'s Annals in Engliſh, Page 113, 114, and 115. and you will find that in the <hi>Rebellion of the North,</hi> (which was the firſt in her Reign,) though <hi>Chapine Vitelli,</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Cotona,</hi> was ſent over to Head Forces, which the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> had promiſed the Rebels; and <hi>Nicholas Morton,</hi> a Prieſt, was ſent at the ſame time by the Pope to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> a Heretick; yet moſt of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſent the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters they received from the Rebels, together with the Bearers of them, to the Queen. Page 125, 126. you may read Pope <hi>Pius</hi>'s Bull againſt the <hi>Queen,</hi> and that the modeſter <hi>Papiſts</hi> miſlik'd it, and were unwilling to bring Miſchief upon themſelves; nay, the beginning of the next Page tells you, <hi>they contemned it as a vain crack of Words.</hi> Page 218. the Papiſts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſuch diſlike of <hi>Parſon</hi>'s fiery zeal againſt the <hi>Queen,</hi> that they thought themſelves to have delivered him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi>'s hands. Page 248. the <hi>Romans Catholicks</hi> miſlike the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in <hi>Politicks,</hi> of their <hi>Prieſts;</hi> and <hi>J. Biſhop,</hi> a Man devoted to the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> writes againſt them, and againſt the <hi>Depoſing Doctrine.</hi> Other paſſages might be quoted out of that Hiſtory; but here are enough, and perhaps ſome will think too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, for whoſe purpoſe it makes more to render the <hi>Papiſts errant Monſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though, by reaſon that our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries are likelieſt to be believed againſt the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice <hi>Our Cauſe</hi> by the general Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice that is againſt them, I have been the more particular about that Party; yet I thank God no Man is leſs liable to be proſelyted to their Opinions in matters of Church-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, than I am, or more loves, or will venture farther in all Times for the <hi>Characteriſtick Liberties</hi> of the Engliſh Subject; <hi>Liberties</hi> that I will defend, as far as in me
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61333:5"/>lies, not only from all <hi>Foreign Powers,</hi> but from all Encroachments of our own <hi>Monarchs</hi> too; though I muſt ſay at the ſame time, that I can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs,</hi> and like our own true and ancient <hi>Hereditary</hi> and <hi>equal Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> the beſt of all the ſeveral ſorts of <hi>Government;</hi> and know alſo that there are many <hi>Prerogatives</hi> that are as neceſſary for the Protection of the <hi>People,</hi> as for the Safety and Grandeur of the <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The World is much miſtaken in our <hi>Notions;</hi> I wiſh they would hear 'em from our ſelves, who can beſt tell the Reaſons of our <hi>Diſſent</hi> from the <hi>preſent Government,</hi> and with what Deſigns, and how far we do, and will ſerve <hi>K. James;</hi> and they will find even the <hi>Non Swearers of the Church of</hi> England have in their <hi>Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> to <hi>Him</hi> a due regard to their <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> likewiſe. By this frankneſs all Parties might come to underſtand one another better, and the late Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments have made all thoſe of the ſeveral Parties, that are for <hi>K. James</hi> wiſer and more temperate than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; the <hi>Jacobites</hi> wiſh their own Diſappointments had made the <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamites</hi> as much ſo; we know in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they have made many of them wiſer.</p>
            <p>We are ſo far from wiſhing the King of <hi>France</hi> ſhould Conquer us, that we don't wiſh King <hi>James</hi> ſhould. We will receive Him, we will help Him, as our <hi>Father,</hi> as our <hi>King;</hi> but <hi>Conqueror</hi> is not in the Language of our Loyalty. The <hi>Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> have been ever thought to carry the Notions of <hi>Prerogative</hi> the higheſt; but I believe amongſt the <hi>Non Swearing Clergy,</hi> there will not be found one St. <hi>Aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ph,</hi> one <hi>Burnet;</hi> and we are heartily glad, that thoſe who ſit in the Two <hi>Houſes</hi> ordered ſuch a <hi>Stigma</hi> for ſuch <hi>nauſeous Flattery:</hi> And ſhould the King be forced to reduce theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms by a high Hand, which many of the <hi>Jacobites</hi> are ſure he is very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to do, and we hope the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> will be wiſer than to put him to it; yet even then all the wiſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluencing <hi>Jacobites</hi> will interpoſe, will keep him (if he ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to do otherwiſe) from pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Revenge, and will tell him, that the end of <hi>Civil War</hi> muſt be attended with Moderation in the <hi>Conqueror;</hi> or otherwiſe he that is one day <hi>Victor</hi> by the <hi>Sword,</hi> may be vanquiſhed the next by <hi>Jealouſies.</hi> If he ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifully devour even his <hi>Rebellious Subjects,</hi> we our ſelves ſhould ſtand affrighted at him, as at a <hi>Polyphemus,</hi> and conclude he would feaſt upon us at laſt. Our <hi>Henry</hi> the Third had like to have loſt himſelf by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate uſe of his Victory over the <hi>Barons:</hi> And <hi>Edward</hi> the Second did loſe himſelf by uſing extream Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gours after his Victory at <hi>Burton</hi> upon <hi>Trent:</hi> Other inſtances of this ſort may be found in our own Hiſtories; and if we rightly conſider the preſent State of Affairs, the <hi>Defection</hi> was very general, and upon the Account of <hi>Male Adminiſtration,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Pardon</hi> ought to be without Exceptions; and a <hi>Rectification</hi> of thoſe Errors will reſtore the <hi>King</hi> to the Hearts of all his People, as well as his Kingdoms, without Effuſion of Blood. They are <hi>State-Quacks,</hi> who only underſtand <hi>Phlebotomy.</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:61333:5"/>A <hi>good Phyſician</hi> will ſweeten and compoſe the Maſs of Humors, and by proper <hi>Lenitives</hi> quiet all our boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Spirits, and correct the Temper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament of the <hi>State</hi> into <hi>Obedience,</hi> without creating Faintneſſes, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying our Vitals. This all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable <hi>Jacobites</hi> are now ſatisfied of, this is their Opinion. It is not the <hi>Title</hi> of the King that is the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute; then indeed Wiſe Kings have, after Victories, been ſevere, as our <hi>Henry</hi> VII. was; but the ſame <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> VII. was as Merciful in <hi>Flammock</hi>'s <hi>Rebellion,</hi> tho' it was occaſion'd by collecting Taxes that were granted by <hi>Parliament.</hi> His Son alſo, <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> VIII. (who was a Prince of a high mind) when 30000 were in Arms in the <hi>Yorkſhire Rebellion,</hi> which was upon account of what they thought <hi>Male-adminiſtration,</hi> pardoned every Man, and after quieted their minds by ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down a Book amongſt them to explain his Intentions. It is by Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and letting us ſee clearly into his Royal Heart, that our King, King <hi>JAMES,</hi> muſt eſtabliſh his Throne; and even they who believe <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> would not be <hi>active</hi> in the Deſtruction of their Country; and tho' they think the <hi>Church of England</hi> ſupports the <hi>Monarchy,</hi> yet now they are ſatisfied nothing leſs will ſecure their <hi>Church,</hi> than what makes our <hi>Liberties</hi> ſafe. You know there are others in his Intereſt, who will claim their Rights in a bolder manner yet; I bleſs God there are many of them, ſome of whom never touched with this Government, and others who have been ſo diſappointed by its <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> and <hi>Adminiſtration,</hi> that they no longer expect a Cure from the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s hands; you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think either the One or the Other of theſe deſire to be a <hi>Conquered Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> nor do I know any one Man that deſires it.</p>
            <p>Indeed this Government has taken all Methods by <hi>Harraſſing</hi> and <hi>Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Taxes</hi> as muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do us, to make the <hi>Jacobites</hi> do ſome deſperate thing: and if any thing would, ſuch Uſage would make us wiſh for a <hi>French Conqueſt,</hi> or any other Change of Torments; but nothing can make us wiſh for a <hi>French Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</hi> They have not yet made us Riſe, that they might have the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcation of our Fortunes, and du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King <hi>William Conquerour without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul:</hi> I hope we ſhall never <hi>Riſe,</hi> till we do it to the purpoſe, till the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion riſes with us; I hope we ſhall diſappoint that Deſign of parcelling out our Inheritances amongſt the ſworn Vaſſals of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> as <hi>Ireland</hi> (which could eaſily have been made to follow the Fortune of <hi>England</hi> at the beginning of this <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution,</hi> had not this Project been in their Head) has been ſhared amongſt them. I hope we ſhall diſappoint them here by a wiſe and temperate Conduct. They care not what <hi>Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> what <hi>Diſtreſſes,</hi> they bring upon, the Nation: but We would reſtore <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Plenty</hi> to it; and whatever our Enemies ſay (who have all along had a great Faculty of contriving Lies, and forming <hi>Hobgoblins</hi>) we love our Country, our <hi>Native</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try too well to let any Uneaſineſs make us have one Thought, one Wiſh for a <hi>French Conqueſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration ſays, One of the Ends of his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61333:6"/>coming was to cover all Men from <hi>Perſecution.</hi> He has kept that as well as the other parts; for he cannot but know that many of thoſe who refuſe the <hi>Oaths,</hi> do it out of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and how many (againſt whom no other Crime has been proved, but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal of thoſe <hi>Oaths,</hi> and therefore in the ſight of the Law guilty of none elſe) have had their <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Horſes ſeized,</hi> have been hindred from fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing their <hi>Lawful Buſineſs,</hi> put to find <hi>unreaſonable Bail,</hi> been laid up in <hi>loathſom Priſons,</hi> and been forced to pay moſt part, if not all their <hi>Incomes?</hi> If this is not <hi>Perſecution,</hi> I know not what is; and I think he cannot but believe it is generally for Conſcience-ſake. Is not that Venerable Old Man Archbiſhop <hi>Sancroft,</hi> and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>dignify'd Perſons,</hi> who have ſhewn a ſufficient Concern for the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty</hi> was not ſo ſtupid (to uſe Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi>'s Epithete) but that they ſtood up for the <hi>Laws.</hi> Are not many of theſe <hi>Excellent Perſons</hi> reduc'd to great <hi>Straights</hi> and <hi>Poverty,</hi> becauſe they have not <hi>ſupple time-ſerving-Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Conſciences?</hi> How many of the <hi>Inferiour Clergy</hi> are ſent to beg their Bread, who made it a point of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to oppoſe the <hi>Irregularities of King James's Miniſters,</hi> who, tho' they would have been, and are now willing to conſent to <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> Parliamentarily ſettled, were not flexible to the <hi>Tricks</hi> ſet on foot by thoſe <hi>deſigning Miniſters?</hi> There has been already, I think, a ſufficient <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution</hi> of the <hi>Jacobites;</hi> but the <hi>Judges</hi> are commanded to ſet a greater for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtill: however, that ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke us to a raſh Attempt, neither to hurt our <hi>ſelves</hi> nor our <hi>Country,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make King <hi>William</hi>'s Hotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potch Title a <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> nor to think of a <hi>French Conqueſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We cannot ſwear away our <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> which we owe to King <hi>James,</hi> as his Birth right, and which moſt of us have ſworn to him; but if it had been thought fit to contrive an Oath, which ſhould have expreſſed our <hi>Love of England,</hi> and our <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence</hi> of a <hi>French Conqueſt,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Mulct had been laid upon the Refuſal of it, whoever had refuſed it would have been by us unpity'd, tho' you had exacted the Mulct never ſo ſeverely, for we are all ſatisfied a <hi>French Conqueſt</hi> is not deſirable.</p>
            <p>That a <hi>French Conqueſt</hi> is contrary to the Inclinations and Intereſts of the ſeveral ſorts of <hi>Jacobites,</hi> is a good Argument that it is not <hi>practicable.</hi> But now I fall upon my ſecond Head, I preſume I ſhall directly and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragably make out. I hat a <hi>French Conqueſt</hi> is not <hi>Practicable;</hi> and that, by ſhewing,</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>That a</hi> French Conqueſt <hi>is as little King</hi> James'<hi>s</hi> Inclination <hi>as his</hi> Intereſt.</item>
               <item>II. <hi>That ſuch a</hi> Conqueſt <hi>is palpably oppoſite to the Intereſt of all the</hi> Princes <hi>and</hi> States <hi>of</hi> Europe.</item>
               <item>And laſtly, <hi>That to attempt a</hi> French Conqueſt <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>either for Himſelf or</hi> King James, <hi>is not the Intereſt of the King of</hi> France <hi>himſelf.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I omit ſhewing a <hi>French Conqueſt</hi> is againſt the Intereſt of King <hi>James,</hi> for I don't think it worth my while to prove that it is againſt a Man's <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:61333:6"/>to have his <hi>Eſtate</hi> taken from him, and his <hi>Poſterity</hi> deſtroy'd. King <hi>James</hi> has a <hi>Child,</hi> that He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves, and <hi>you</hi> believe too (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the pains you take to be thought to believe that uſeful Flam of your pretended <hi>Impoſture,</hi> which was at firſt taken up, and induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly promoted (like that of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> cutting the Throats of all the People of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi>) to help for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward this <hi>Revolution</hi>) to be <hi>a True</hi> PRINCE OF WALES; and at leaſt, this innocent Child has not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oblig'd the <hi>King;</hi> and this is enough to make him take pity of the <hi>Nation,</hi> however Rebellious and Ungrateful we have been to him: But beſides, he has ſeveral times ſince his <hi>Exile</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed himſelf in ſo pathetick and extenuating a Style concerning thoſe Subjects that have uſed him ſo ill, that it would be almoſt incredible, if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated; And tho' the <hi>Prince of Wales</hi> was dead, he retains even for the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> ſuch a Fatherly Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as plainly ſuperſedes Royal Reſentment; and I have heard one that was by ſay, That upon a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's mentioning, even upon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Buſineſs, the Fault of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> and that with all the Modeſty imaginable, (and he muſt touch very tenderly upon that String who will make his Court to the King, tho' ſuch virulent Pamphlets are Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed here againſt Him), the King reply'd <q>That the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> had Natural Foundations of Good neſs that <hi>Dr. Burnet</hi> and the <hi>Biſhop of London</hi> can never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </q> And further, they who have been at S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mans</hi> k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow with what Indignation the <hi>King</hi> treats althoughts of Reſtoring him by any other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod than by <hi>a great Concurrence of his own People.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> knows how obſtinately the People of <hi>Britain,</hi> nay, many that are <hi>now</hi> his own Friends, would reſiſt any other Method; and he knows that the <hi>Riches</hi> of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try are the <hi>People</hi> of it: He would be <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and he would have his <hi>Son,</hi> the <hi>King of Great Britain;</hi> and he does not think it worth his while to be King of <hi>Trees,</hi> of <hi>Beaſts,</hi> and a <hi>deſolated Land,</hi> or to leave ſuch a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd Kingdom to his Son. When I weigh the good Inclinations of the King, and the barbarous Perſecution and Miſrepreſentation he has met with, I am ſhook with a double Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: I compaſſionate <hi>His Wrongs,</hi> and am aſtoniſhed at <hi>our Ingratitude,</hi> and that we would not once try whether the Things we complain'd of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from <hi>His own Nature,</hi> or from <hi>thoſe about him,</hi> whom the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had corrupted. The Scene of <hi>His</hi> and <hi>our</hi> Miſeries is abundantly and admirably laid open in an excellent Book printed laſt Summer, called, <hi>Great Britain's Juſt Complaint;</hi> and if I would entertain the World upon that Subject, I muſt either tranſcribe what may be found in that Book, or relate the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the ſame Matter of Fact, without doing the ſame Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to the Cauſe of the King. That Great and Judicious Author has diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd the whole <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity;</hi> How ſuch Snares were laid for the King as an honeſt-minded Man could ſcarce eſcape; How willing the King was to redreſs our Grievances, when he found he had been in Miſtakes, and this before he went away; How he continued in the <hi>ſame Mind</hi> when he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61333:7"/>was addreſſed to by ſome of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who had <hi>appeared moſt vigorouſly to reſent thoſe Miſtakes,</hi> and this when he was under no Preſſure in his Affairs. I will add no more to juſtifie the Inclinations of the King, but beſeech every body who reads this to read <hi>Great Britain's Juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint,</hi> which puts the Nation upon the beſt Method for us to know the Inclinations of our King. He adviſes, page 48. <q>to reſume that Treaty we ſo fooliſhly broke off and refuſed, and thereby to ſecure Religion and Property by thoſe <hi>Conceſſions</hi> which our Sovereign is ſtill ready to grant us. He goes on, "Let us put it home to him, and lay it at his own Door; Let him have it in his choice to return by his People, if he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Convince him, that his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Subjects, upon ſecuring their Religion and Liberties, will repair their former Errors, by contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting heartily towards his Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And, as that Author ſays, if he declines to return upon a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant and Engliſh Foot, there is an end of the Controverſie, and of all Diſputes amongſt Proteſtants; for Religion and Liberty will never be ſacrificed by true Engliſh-men.</q> And I will add to what he ſays, If no true <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> joyn with him, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Forces they can tranſport upon us, neither can King <hi>James</hi> come home, nor can the <hi>French</hi> conquer us: But, God be praiſed, a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny true <hi>Engliſh men</hi> will joyn to bring home the King, tho' I know not one ſo bad an <hi>Engliſh man</hi> as would join in a <hi>French Conqueſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I come in the ſecond place to ſhew, That it is not the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of any of the Princes or States of <hi>Europe,</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> ſhould make us a <hi>Conqueſt.</hi> The excellent Author of the abovenamed <hi>Great Britain's. Juſt Complaint</hi> has proved, that whether this <hi>Confederate War</hi> ends ſucceſsfully or unſucceſsfully, in all likelihood, and according to all the Rules of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy,</hi> the <hi>Reſtauration of King James</hi> muſt in a ſhort time follow upon the Determination of it: But it is my buſineſs to make it plain, That tho' it may be, and is the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries to have King <hi>James</hi> Reſtored at the concluſion of this War, yet it is not the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of any of them, that the <hi>French</hi> ſhould conquer us, have our Kings their Vaſſals, or be Maſters of our Ports. Would the <hi>Spaniard</hi> have the Chanel ſhut up on both ſides to <hi>Flanders?</hi> Would the <hi>Dutch</hi> have the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh Ports</hi> managed by ſuch <hi>ſelect Committees,</hi> as the <hi>French</hi> would infallibly ſet up for Trade? And how long would the <hi>Dutch</hi> reſiſt <hi>Ours</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Power, united under one <hi>Abſolute Monarch?</hi> Would not the <hi>Northern Crowns,</hi> and all the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> ſoon feel the Weight of ſuch a Confluence of Strength? The Influence that ſuch a <hi>Conqueſt</hi> would have upon all the States of <hi>Europe,</hi> be they never ſo remote, is at firſt ſight ſo evident, that there is not one of them who would be an idle Spectator of our Ruine. Every body now knows the Danger their own Houſe is in, when their Neighbor's is on fire. Every little <hi>Politician</hi> knows how much Greatneſs depends upon <hi>Naval Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations and Trade;</hi> therefore every body would be allarm'd, every body in an Uproar, when they ſaw ſuch
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61333:7"/>
               <hi>Maritime Kingdoms</hi> as ours like to be made an Acceſſion to the numerous <hi>Land-Forces</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> They are idle Brains, that dream of <hi>Univerſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies</hi> at this day; and tho' whole Kingdoms heretofore would not join in a Common Defence, whole <hi>Europe</hi> would now. However Ambitious the King of <hi>France</hi> may be, he can never think of ſo unweildy a Project, in which he muſt not only encounter all <hi>England,</hi> all this Iſland, all theſe Three Kingdoms, but all <hi>Europe</hi> too.</p>
            <p>I come in the laſt place to ſhew, That it is not the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the K. of <hi>France</hi> to attempt to make us a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,</hi> either for <hi>Himſelf</hi> or K. <hi>James.</hi> I would ask but two things to be granted me, which I think will be granted by moſt Men: The one is, That the King of <hi>France</hi> tolerably un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands his own <hi>Intereſt;</hi> The other is, That he will follow it where he finds it. And now I ſhall proceed to prove, That it is not the Intereſt of <hi>France</hi> to attempt to make us a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</hi> The Unweildineſs of the Project is one very good Reaſon againſt it. Leſs than One hundred thouſand of his beſt Men cannot make us a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,</hi> and keep us ſo; and he muſt only take Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Land,</hi> and not expect to be Maſter of the <hi>People,</hi> by reaſon of our <hi>Religion;</hi> and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſends to be his <hi>Lieutenant</hi> here, will be under great Temptation to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt from him, and ſet up for himſelf, or become the Firſt Subject of theſe Kingdoms, which we ſhall be willing to make him, and a greater Subject than <hi>France</hi> has, rather than not get rid of the Miſeries of a <hi>Provincial,</hi> and be reſtored to our own Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Conſider how much danger the <hi>Abſolute Power of France</hi> will run by a too free intercourſe with the few ſurviving <hi>Britains,</hi> who will acquaint ſo many of his Soldiers what were the <hi>Freedoms</hi> of our Land. Conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>France</hi> can bear ſuch an Evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation as is neceſſary to Make and People us a <hi>Province.</hi> We believe that the Expulſion of the <hi>Hugonots</hi> let out too much of his People, too much of the Vital Blood of <hi>France:</hi> It did ſo doubtleſs, and a Plantation of our <hi>Iſland</hi> would endanger all he has up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Continent.</hi> What Neighbor that envies him, would not be glad to ſee him make ſuch an Experiment, would not nick the lucky Opportunity, and pull back all thoſe Towns and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, which he may now much more eaſily <hi>keep,</hi> than he can <hi>gain</hi> us? Would any <hi>Peace,</hi> any <hi>Leagues</hi> they can have with him, be Proof againſt ſuch a promiſing Temptation? To at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> of theſe Kingdoms would indeed be graſping at a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious <hi>Shadow,</hi> but he would not fail to loſe a great deal of real <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi> The King of <hi>France</hi> is not ſuch a <hi>Knight-Errant,</hi> he does not love to venture over much: He, like <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> when he had attain'd the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, loves to make good what he gets, and is not like the <hi>Macedonian Rambler,</hi> greedy of difficult and bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Travels. Let the Deſigns of <hi>France</hi> be as vaſt as they will, their <hi>King</hi> is no Madman. <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Tiberius</hi> (who were both skilful in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) are thought by very ſenſible Men to have neglected <hi>Britain</hi> out of this wholſom State-Maxim <hi>That it was neceſſary to bound and moderate the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Empire.</hi> It is certain thoſe two Emperors often thought of bounding
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61333:8"/>the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> and of bringing it into a tenable Compaſs; and it is plain, that mighty Empire was at laſt overthrown by its own Weight and Largeneſs. The <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> of <hi>France</hi> is of a prodigious growth for this Age, and if the King of <hi>France</hi> thinks of ſubduing ſuch a brave and popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Countrey as we are, ſo united as we ſhall be, when we find only the <hi>French King's</hi> Intereſt at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the <hi>Plot,</hi> and ſo aſſiſted as we ſhall be by all the <hi>Potentates of Europe</hi> for their own ſakes, he will miſcarry in the Enterprize, and <hi>France</hi> it ſelf will tumble from its Highth. It is a bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Undertaking, than what is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of <hi>Alexander the Great;</hi> and thô the King of <hi>France</hi> ſhould overrun us, he would, like that <hi>Alexander,</hi> never be able to ſettle a Government a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, but his very Victories would ſhake his own.</p>
            <p>Let it be farther conſidered, That though the <hi>French</hi> have been ſucceſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Wars near home, yet they have been unſucceſsful in remote Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, where either the tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Sea, or the uneaſineſs of the paſſage by Land have rendred Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours hard and difficult to be ſent. What rendred all their Attempts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> and Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of <hi>Milan</hi> ineffectual, but the difficulties they found in ſending Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies to <hi>Naples</hi> by Sea and to <hi>Milan</hi> over the rough <hi>Alpes?</hi> In our King <hi>John</hi>'s time <hi>Lewis,</hi> the then <hi>Dauphine</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> was invited over and ſworn to by many of the <hi>Barons;</hi> But did not the difficulty of getting Supplies to maintain his footing at laſt utterly defeat all his Hopes? Would not our preſent <hi>Sailers</hi> carry their Ships to any part of the World, rather than let them be carried into <hi>France?</hi> Is there not think you <hi>one Great Man left,</hi> whoſe Fidelity to our own <hi>right Line,</hi> and whoſe Courage and Vigilance is equal to <hi>Hubert de Burgh</hi>'s? Think you there is no Gallant Man, who would by a Sea-fight hinder the pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of freſh <hi>French</hi> Succours, when we ſaw they aimed at the Diſtruction of the <hi>Right</hi> of our <hi>Royal Family,</hi> and our own <hi>Rights?</hi> I am not over fond of the preſent Age, yet there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Brave and Loyal Men in it, that would defeat any <hi>French Deſign</hi> that were injurious to our own <hi>legal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</hi> But to come to our own Days; What enabled <hi>Spain</hi> to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Catalonia</hi> in a great meaſure, and to pluck <hi>Meſſina</hi> in <hi>Sicily</hi> out of the preſent King of <hi>France</hi>'s hands, when they were loſing Ground in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining <hi>Provinces,</hi> but the difficulty of ſending Supplies to the one over the <hi>Pyrenean Mountains,</hi> and to the other by <hi>Sea?</hi> And it is remarkable, That the uncertainties alone of <hi>Wind</hi> and <hi>Weather</hi> rendred the ſuppling of <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſina</hi> impracticable, even when the <hi>French</hi> were Maſters of the <hi>Seas,</hi> and had routed the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleets, and killed the famous <hi>de Ruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> How much more will the ſame uncertainties of Wind and Weather, joyn'd with our <hi>brave Ships,</hi> and <hi>braver Sea-men</hi> render us ſafe, and all ſuch Deſigns as a <hi>French Conqueſt</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable? Did not alſo this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King of <hi>France</hi> in our own Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories over-run like a violent Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> and poſſeſs himſelf of a great part of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and yet was obliged to throw up all his <hi>Conqueſts?</hi> And for what Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61333:8"/>Becauſe there was the interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of fifty or ſixty Miles that was not his own, which might have hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the ſending Supplies, and will not the interpoſition of more Miles of a tempeſtuous and uncertain Sea, joyned with the Rebuffs which will be given him by our Fleet, lay greater Rubs in his way, and oblige him at laſt to diſgorge, tho' he ſhould by ſurprize gain Ground upon us? What was it induced the <hi>Romans</hi> to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Fourſcore thouſand Men in <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and to ſecure their Frontiers in this Iſland, by the famous Walls of <hi>Adrian</hi> and <hi>Severus,</hi> as well as with ſuch numerous Troops, againſt the Incurſions of the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Picts,</hi> who were confin'd within the little Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try now called <hi>Scotland;</hi> when at the ſame time they were able to protect their Frontiers with leſs numerous Troops from the Inſults of the <hi>Parthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and of the <hi>Germans</hi> (which then included all modern <hi>Germany</hi> to the <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Eaſt</hi> of the <hi>Danube</hi> and <hi>Rhine,</hi> the <hi>Northern Crowns, Poland,</hi> and better part of <hi>Muſcovy</hi>) each of which Nations taken ſeparately did poſſeſs Countries ſix times bigger than <hi>France</hi> at this day? Was it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the difficulty of ſending Troops into <hi>Britain,</hi> occaſion'd by the uncertainty of Wind and Weather, tho' they were Maſters of the Seas, and their Enemies had no Fleet to oppoſe them? What Reaſon then have the <hi>French</hi> to dream of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of our Iſland, when all its Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants are united in one <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Government;</hi> when all Nations are now equaliſed as to Arms and Diſcipline of War, and when our Fleet, modeſtly ſpeaking, is <hi>equal</hi> to any of our Neighbors? Would it be reaſonable for them, with Forces leſs conſiderable than thoſe of the <hi>Romans,</hi> with fewer Incouragements from the Advantage of Military Diſcipline and Arms (in which the <hi>Romans</hi> did far ſurpaſs their Enemies) and under ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more Diſcouragements from our Fleet and otherwiſe, to attempt the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> of a People much more Great, Rich and Numerous, than the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Picts,</hi> who have the ſenſe of <hi>Religion</hi> as well as <hi>Liberty,</hi> of all that is dear and valuable, to rouze and influence their Courages; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when from all Hiſtories Foreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers may learn this Leſſon: That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs than an <hi>Annihilation</hi> can extinguiſh the ſenſe of <hi>Religion, Honor,</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> in <hi>Engliſh Breaſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think I have already ſhewn, That it is not the Intereſt of <hi>France</hi> to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to make us a <hi>Conqueſt</hi> for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: And it is as eaſie to ſhew, It is as little their Intereſt to make us <hi>Slaves</hi> to King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am reſolv'd I will advance what will be thought a <hi>Paradox,</hi> viz. That there is no one Countrey ſo much concerned as <hi>France,</hi> that we ſhould have good Securities for our <hi>Liberties</hi> under the <hi>Reſtauration;</hi> and if I am challenged on this Head, I can make this Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox plain to every body's Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. I ſhall touch upon it brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here. <hi>France</hi> is concern'd to keep us from an <hi>Abſolute Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> too, and that by reaſon of our <hi>Pretences</hi> upon that Kingdom. It would be the greateſt <hi>Sol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eciſm</hi> in the French <hi>Politicks</hi> to make a King, that has ſuch a Claim, entire Maſter of a People, who have ſuch natural Courage, and that love <hi>Glory</hi> rather
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61333:9"/>too immoderately, or to remove ſuch a <hi>Shiboleth,</hi> as are our different <hi>Creeds.</hi> It is the Intereſt of <hi>France</hi> to promote and head our Diſcontents, and not to lay the People at the <hi>King's</hi> Mercy. They thought ſo formerly, and of late years. Did not <hi>Lewis</hi> mention'd, in my laſt Paragraph, before he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this Realm, take care that <hi>Hen</hi> 3. ſhould give his Oath, nay made him give it; That he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore to the <hi>Barons</hi> of the Realm, and other his Subjects all their Rights and Priviledges, for which the Diſcord began between King <hi>John</hi> and his People; <hi>Baker</hi>'s Chronicle, P. 114? Did not their great <hi>Richelieu</hi> at the beginning of our late <hi>Civil Wars</hi> ſend <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> into <hi>Scotland</hi> to ſtir up the <hi>Male Contents,</hi> and that though we had ſo lately married a Daughter of <hi>France,</hi> and ſo lately had had a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with the <hi>Spaniard?</hi> Their Kings muſt be ready to aſſiſt the People, if their Rights are in real Danger; or, when we have loſt <hi>our Rights,</hi> they may loſe <hi>their Crowns.</hi> 
               <q>The Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of Neighbouring Princes ſeldom laſt long, ſeldom during their own Lives, and are more ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom tranſmitted to their Poſterities. Many Reaſons and Jealouſies of State are falling in, which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion frequent and unavoidable Breaches, and a King of <hi>England</hi> who is Abſolute and Maſter of his Subjects may be troubleſome and dangerous to <hi>France,</hi> and may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive our Old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pretences to the moſt conſiderable Provinces, <hi>nay to the Crown of</hi> France <hi>its ſelf.</hi>
               </q> So that it will be prudent in the <hi>French</hi> King to let us alone with our old Quarrels between <hi>Prerogative</hi> and <hi>Privilege,</hi> and let our Eaſe be a check upon the Ambition of our Princes, when a daring and enterpriſing Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit may be upon the Throne, one who may be willing to court Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Dangers, and try for what his Forefathers have poſſeſſed. The King of <hi>France</hi> is ſo far from <hi>deſigning a Conqueſt for himſelf,</hi> that <hi>he deſires no Retribution for what King</hi> James <hi>his Misfortunes have coſt him.</hi> And this I ſay from <hi>good Authority.</hi> And as for <hi>Conquering for King</hi> James, he too well knows his own Intereſt to think it ſo, to make us <hi>Slaves</hi> or <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>either</hi> of them. Of this you may read more in <hi>Great Britain's Juſt Complaint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know how artful and indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our Adverſaries are, and that tho' a Man beats them out of all their ſtrong holds, yet they will at laſt retire and betake themſelves to thoſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that they in their own minds know have no real weight; and I therefore foreſee they will ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſcare Men with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of all our former <hi>pretended Conqueſts;</hi> and for that reaſon, and that there may remain no umbrage, not even the leaſt to imagin a <hi>French Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi> practicable, I will take every one of thoſe <hi>Conqueſts</hi> into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and handle them apart, that I may treat of them more diſtinctly: and I preſume the Reflections I ſhall make upon them will ſhew not only a vaſt difference between the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Circumſtances of thoſe that are ſaid to be our <hi>Conquerors,</hi> and the preſent <hi>French Power,</hi> and between the State of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Affairs <hi>then,</hi> and what they are <hi>now,</hi> but alſo ſhew a great diſparity between the <hi>Intereſts</hi> that thoſe <hi>Invaders</hi> propoſed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61333:9"/>and what the King of <hi>France</hi> can have at this day: So that whether in a genuine and ſtrict ſenſe they were <hi>Conqueſts</hi> or no, I hope to make it plain that they will in no wiſe over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Poſitions I have been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing.</p>
            <p>If any man has a mind to examin whether they were properly <hi>Conqueſts,</hi> he muſt conſult our <hi>Antiquities,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Treatiſes</hi> that are expreſly writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on that Subject, wherein he will find the Point warmly debated on both ſides, and perhaps with more <hi>Heat</hi> than <hi>Judgment;</hi> I will refer this <hi>Enquirer</hi> to thoſe <hi>Authors,</hi> and ſall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to conſider our ſeveral <hi>Invaders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will begin with <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Invaſion, which was the firſt of which we have any certain knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> who was then only an Officer of the <hi>Roman</hi> State, but had laid in his own Breaſt the Deſign of ſeizing upon that Empire, when he had ſubdued moſt part of the ancient <hi>Gallia,</hi> (which comprehends the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>France, Savoy, Switzerland, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> on this ſide the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi>) and by a Potent Faction at <hi>Rome</hi> had obtained it of the Senate as his Province for many years, thought it neceſſary to add to the Glory of his Name ſome Attempt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Countries beyond the end of the World, (for ſo was <hi>Britain</hi> in thoſe days thought at <hi>Rome,</hi>) that ſo his <hi>dazling Achievements</hi> might make his long intended purpoſe more eaſie: I mean, his Deſign of raiſing himſelf from a <hi>Servant</hi> to be <hi>Maſter of his Country.</hi> As to the <hi>Romans</hi> themſelves, when they came firſt amongſt us, their Power was united, entire, and ſo much too big for all our Neighboring Countries, that they had given Law to every one of them before they had attempted Us, and we were divided into ſeveral petty Governments, who would not joyn in a common Defence.</p>
            <p>Give me leave now to ſet down, That the King of <hi>France</hi> is already at the Head of a <hi>Government,</hi> and needs not riſque what he has, to make him Superior to thoſe amongſt whom he dwells. We are united under one <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</hi> There are many Princes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate againſt <hi>France,</hi> that are very Powerful; and Neutral Princes enough to turn at any time the Scale: Nor is there, as I ſaid, amongſt all the <hi>Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites</hi> that I know, one Man who ſo little loves his own <hi>King</hi> and his own <hi>Country,</hi> as that he would not hazard his Life againſt the <hi>French,</hi> if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned any thing in prejudice of our <hi>Rightful Monarch</hi> or <hi>his Poſterity,</hi> or our <hi>Conſtitution</hi> it ſelf. Can any Man think we have leſs ſenſe of <hi>Liberty</hi> than the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who yet had not a different <hi>Religion</hi> to caution them, as the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Jacobites</hi> have here? Indeed ſome of us are (like them) ſometimes wheedl'd into too early and undue Suſpicions of the <hi>French,</hi> even by the <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> of the <hi>Prince of Orange;</hi> and if any body talks of governing <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by <hi>French Power,</hi> I am ſure they muſt be the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi>'s <hi>Penſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> and tho' the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> himſelf is not good at <hi>Much,</hi> his Agents have the Art to foment <hi>Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides all this, there is a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parity between the <hi>Times</hi> in which the <hi>Romans</hi> came hither, and <hi>now,</hi> by reaſon of our Skill in Military Affairs. I ſuppoſe few <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men will allow the <hi>French</hi> ſo much ſuperior to us in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61333:10"/>the Art of War, as the <hi>Romans</hi> were to the naked <hi>Britains.</hi> Our late Taxes have been very ill beſtow'd, if our Fleet does not hold the ſame Diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion; and yet in thoſe days, tho' the <hi>Romans</hi> were ſo long amongſt us, and tho' they govern'd us in great part by our own Laws, and many of their <hi>Lieutenants</hi> rather taught us the exerciſe of, than took away our <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> nevertheleſs they never had (if our beſt Hiſtorians may be credited) the whole Land at any one time in Subjection; and tho' ſuch Multitudes of the <hi>Britains</hi> were ſlain, the Tribute the <hi>Romans</hi> got here coſt them, in <hi>Maſſacres</hi> and <hi>Battels,</hi> more Men than <hi>France</hi> will ever be able to ſpend upon the Project of <hi>Conquering theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moſt of what is recorded of the manner of the coming, and being here of the <hi>Romans,</hi> is handed down to us by their own Writers, with a naked and ſedate Narration: but <hi>Cloyſter'd Clergy-men</hi> (who uſed themſelves to write <hi>Hyperboles</hi> rather than preciſe <hi>Truths</hi>) being thoſe from whom we have moſt of our Accounts of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Times, we muſt expect ſwelling and <hi>Legendary</hi> Reports; but that wherein I ſhall conſider, to ſhew the diſparity between <hi>them</hi> and the <hi>French,</hi> and <hi>ours</hi> and <hi>thoſe days,</hi> lies in a ſmall Compaſs, and will be granted on all hands.</p>
            <p>The Quarrels of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire had carry'd into <hi>France,</hi> under the Banners of <hi>Maximus</hi> (one of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors for it) the Flower &amp; Strength of <hi>Britain;</hi> and with the overthrow of <hi>Maximus</hi> by <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> they either all periſhed, or ſeated themſelves in <hi>Armorica.</hi> There was likewiſe another great Tranſplantation of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Youth under <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> and at this time the <hi>Saxons</hi> were a very Warlike People, and ſo over-charg'd with Numbers, that they ſent Multitudes abroad to fight for a Habitation. The Frame of their Government agreed very well with the <hi>Britiſh,</hi> and was very near what are at this day the <hi>Fundamentals</hi> of our <hi>Government:</hi> They were invited in, to preſerve us from being over-run by the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Picts,</hi> who were our <hi>Fellow-Iſlanders;</hi> and tho' I don't doubt the <hi>Saxons</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Merit of their Succeſſes againſt our Enemies further than became our <hi>Friends,</hi> yet I cannot imagin but that there was a more equal <hi>Incorporation</hi> of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Stock than we can diſcover at this diſtance of time, and from ſuch paſſionate Writers as are the Relators of what paſs'd then. And, after all, it was want of <hi>Ships,</hi> and great <hi>Diviſions</hi> amongſt the <hi>Britains,</hi> occaſion'd their Overthrow (for our <hi>Monarchy</hi> was not perfected, and, as <hi>Milton</hi> ſays very well, <hi>Vortigern</hi> was rather <hi>Chief,</hi> than <hi>ſole King.</hi>) Theſe were the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why the <hi>Saxons</hi> ſo far maſtered the <hi>Britains;</hi> and yet the <hi>Saxons</hi> often ran a Riſque of a final Extirpation.</p>
            <p>From this Account of the <hi>Saxon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion,</hi> the diſparity is very obvious. I heartily lament the Loſs of ſo much <hi>Engliſh</hi> Blood as has been ſpilt <hi>unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily</hi> and <hi>unlawfully</hi> too, in theſe our deplorable Diſtractions, into which we have brought our ſelves, by inviting over a <hi>Foreigner</hi> to reſcue thoſe <hi>Liberties,</hi> which he has (as we might well ſuppoſe he would) more <hi>trampled upon</hi> than all the <hi>Evil Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors</hi> of King <hi>James.</hi> We would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite a <hi>Foreign Prince</hi> to do our own
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61333:10"/>proper Work, inſtead of endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Parliamentarily</hi> to redreſs our <hi>Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances,</hi> or reſcuing our ſelves our <hi>Liberties</hi> by an <hi>Engliſh Inſurrection,</hi> ſuch a one as thoſe whereby our Anceſtors obtained the Confirmations of their <hi>Charters,</hi> and which often ended (as all Inſurrections ought to do) without any real Prejudice to the <hi>Succeſſive Monarchy,</hi> and which (let it be call'd now as <hi>Whiggiſh</hi> as they will, and thoſe that were formerly were <hi>Popiſh</hi>) is more juſtifiable either to <hi>Prudence</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> than the <hi>Nobility, Gentlemen,</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">Tho' the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration mentions <hi>Lords Spiritual,</hi> and ſome have raiſed a Scandal upon Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <hi>Sancroft</hi> as if his hand was to the Invitation of him; I am well aſſured that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>that Right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Prelate,</hi> nor his <hi>Fellow Sufferers</hi> ever engaged in that deſign of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling over the P. of <hi>Orange.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Clergy,</hi> (who call themſelves of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) their Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Foreign Prince,</hi> which (with all the Charity and Pity in the World for thoſe who were inconſiderately miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and are not ſo obſtinate as to think with <hi>Catiline,</hi> 
               <q>That <hi>ill</hi> Deeds muſt be made ſafe with <hi>worſe</hi>) I beg leave to ſay was Unnatural, and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of <hi>His Relative,</hi> and <hi>their Civil Duty.</hi>
               </q> I ſay, I heartily lament the Loſs of ſo much <hi>Engliſh</hi> Blood as has been unwarrantably thrown away in <hi>Ireland,</hi> at <hi>Sea,</hi> and in <hi>Flanders;</hi> and yet, God be praiſed, we have ſtill left <hi>generous Youth</hi> enough to make us the Terrour of all <hi>Ambitious Princes,</hi> if we would once again unite to take away all <hi>Diſputes of Title</hi> by reſtoring our <hi>rightful</hi> and <hi>lawful King,</hi> and betake our ſelves to negotiate in the <hi>Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> rather than over haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engage in <hi>Wars abroad,</hi> which <hi>Wars</hi> might be evidently proved <hi>deſtructive</hi> to this Nation; and, would it not too much lengthen this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> would be no unuſeful digreſſion here, ſince our own <hi>woful experience,</hi> from the time we have been <hi>hook'd</hi> into this preſent <hi>Quarrel</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> which is more the <hi>Confederates</hi> than <hi>Ours,</hi> has made it ſo proper a Subject to be well conſidered of. I hope <hi>ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> or other will handle it in a <hi>Paper</hi> apart.</p>
            <p>But I muſt return to ſhew the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparity between the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Affairs <hi>now,</hi> and when the <hi>Saxons</hi> came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and that with a reſpect to the <hi>French</hi> Nation; and I again bleſs God we are not yet drain'd by this <hi>Confederate Quarrel,</hi> we have hand over head ingaged in, of all thoſe <hi>Gallant Man,</hi> that ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our <hi>Iſland.</hi> But farther, Have not the <hi>French</hi> a Land to live in? Is <hi>France</hi> ſo overſtocked with <hi>People?</hi> has <hi>their</hi> Government any Affinity with <hi>ours?</hi> Have we any <hi>Fellow-Iſlanders,</hi> who are of a <hi>diſtinct Government</hi> that endeavour to deſtroy us? And laſtly, Is not our Government reſolved into a natural Monarchy, though, prais'd be God, it is a <hi>limited one?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Danes,</hi> though their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal is diſputed, it is plain by all the Hiſtories of thoſe Times that they were <hi>Rovers</hi> and <hi>Robbers,</hi> that were to ſeek a Countrey to live in, and poſſibly might be another ſwarm of the <hi>Saxons;</hi> and it is obſervable that they were above Two hundred Years before they maſtered this Land; and that the Reaſon they maſtered us at laſt, was our want of <hi>Ships;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had been attacking us about
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61333:11"/>Two hundred Years, they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely Massacred, <hi>Man, Woman</hi> and <hi>Child,</hi> all in leſs than Four and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Hours; and when <hi>Swain</hi> the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> King (which was Two hundred twenty and four Years from the firſt entrance of the <hi>Danes</hi>) had forced King <hi>Ethelred</hi> into <hi>Normandy; Swain</hi> dying the next Year, and the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Army ſetting up <hi>Cannte</hi> or <hi>Knute</hi> his Son, the <hi>Saxon Nobility</hi> and <hi>States</hi> were in ſuch Heart and Power, that they ſent <hi>Meſſengers</hi> to <hi>Ethelred,</hi> Declaring <hi>they preferred none before their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Sovereign, <hi>If he would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to Govern better than he had done;</hi>
               </hi> and accordingly upon his Promiſe to redreſs their <hi>Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> they <hi>repoſſeſſed</hi> him of his <hi>Throne,</hi> and continued it to his Son <hi>Edmond Ironſides</hi> I wiſh our <hi>Engliſh Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> would now ſend <hi>Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> to lay before the <hi>King</hi> all the <hi>Male-Adminiſtrations</hi> of his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and what are the proper <hi>Securities</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſuch <hi>Male-Adminiſtrations</hi> for the future; and I am confident the <hi>King</hi> will receive ſuch a Meſſage very kindly, nay I know from very good Authority he would, and that he is willing to give <hi>mankind</hi> all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Satisfaction. Here I muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve alſo, That there ſtill remained amongſt us diſtinct and quarrelling petty Governments, (for the <hi>Saxon Heptarchy</hi> was not entirely wrought up into a <hi>Natural Monarchy,</hi>) and yet <hi>Edmond Ironſide</hi> had totally routed <hi>Canute,</hi> had it not been for that Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Edrick,</hi> who at the Battle of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd</hi> by ſome Wiles detained <hi>Edmond</hi> from purſuing him, which <hi>Edrick</hi> (as an Example to <hi>Traytors</hi>) was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward put to Death by <hi>Canute.</hi> I have another Remark that I would ſet down concerning the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Matters, which is, That the <hi>Citizens</hi> and <hi>Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of <hi>London</hi> ſtuck by <hi>Edmond Iron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi> but the <hi>Sherlockian-Providential-Archbiſhops, Abbots,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Noble-men</hi> elected the <hi>Conqueror Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute;</hi> as ſome <hi>Biſhops</hi> and too many of our <hi>Nobles</hi> have done the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> I am ſorry that the <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> of <hi>London</hi> have not more unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly ſtuck to their <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Rightful Monarch;</hi> but I hope they will yet have an Opportunity to redeem their Reputation, and that they will then unanimouſly call back their <hi>King,</hi> that they may blot out the Guilt of their too <hi>general Defection;</hi> and tho' too many have joyned with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> yet there are many worthy <hi>Citizens</hi> that have retained their <hi>Ancient Loyalty</hi> during all this <hi>Revolution;</hi> and the Number of thoſe who how ſee their Error daily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth.</p>
            <p>I have digreſſed a little by repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome Things, which are not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſo pertinent to my main De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; and ſince I am turn'd <hi>Story-Tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> I will put down the Reaſon why <hi>Canute</hi> put <hi>Edrick</hi> to Death, which was for ſlaying the <hi>Lord's Anointed, Edmond Ironſide;</hi> and that, though <hi>Edmond</hi> was <hi>Canute</hi>'s Enemy, and yet <hi>Canute</hi> himſelf made away the <hi>Brother</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Edmond,</hi> either of which had a better Right to be the <hi>Lord's Anointed</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> than <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute</hi> had himſelf. This was ſuch a piece of <hi>Juſtica,</hi> as it is now of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> for our <hi>Conquerors, <hi>William</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> to keep with Solemnity the 30th. of Jan. and 29th. of May. But though he was guilty of this Mockery
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61333:11"/>in point of <hi>private Juſtice,</hi> yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of <hi>England</hi> he commanded the Obſervation of the Ancient <hi>Saxon Laws</hi> (which were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards called the <hi>Laws of Edward the</hi> Confeſſor) and at a <hi>Convention</hi> of <hi>Danes</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> it was agreed on between both Parties to revive and keep <hi>thoſe Laws.</hi> I think our preſent Conquerors have not revived many of our <hi>good Old,</hi> or made many <hi>New</hi> advantageous <hi>Laws</hi> for us. It is by <hi>Unreaſonable Fines, Arbitrary Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Preſſing men contrary to Law,</hi> &amp;c. (againſt all which Things the P. of O. his own <hi>Declaration</hi> inveighed, and our <hi>Bill of Rights</hi> provided) that they maintain their Conqueſt. Theſe are their Methods, inſtead of granting the <hi>Judges Bill,</hi> the Bill for<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>I have it from a good hand, That the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before he refuſed the</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ennial Bill, <hi>had in ſome Diſcourſe this Expreſſion,</hi> I hear they think I will paſs the <hi>Triennial Bill;</hi> but I promiſe them, the Crown ſhall be ne'er the worſe for my wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</note>
               <hi>Triennial Parliaments,</hi> and the Bill for <hi>Mines;</hi> theſe are their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, inſtead of court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Love of thoſe they call <hi>their Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will add no more about the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Invaſion,</hi> but that their Empire here laſted not many years, and that their <hi>Kings</hi> who ruled us made this the Seat of their <hi>Dominions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now compare things with reſpect to the <hi>Daniſh Invaſion,</hi> and the preſent poſture of Affairs. I muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſay, the <hi>French</hi> are not a <hi>roving</hi> People, that live by Pillage, and that are deſtitute of a Dwelling; nor would they be willing to engage in a War of ſuch Continuance; nor would their <hi>Monarch</hi> change the ſcituation of his <hi>Palace;</hi> nor can he ſpare from guarding his <hi>Frontiers</hi> ſuch an <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>my</hi> as would be neceſſary to keep us in quiet, tho' we were ſubdu'd by a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fight; nor are we unprovided with Ships, tho' I muſt confeſs I fear the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> has not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo much care of our Fleet, as Mr. <hi>Pepys</hi>'s <hi>Memoires</hi> lately put forth has proved King JAMES did; which ſhews King JAMES under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and proſecuted the <hi>True Engliſh Intereſt,</hi> and is a ſufficient Confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that ſcandalous Aſperſion their celebrated Dr. <hi>King</hi> caſts upon His Majeſty. His expreſſions beſpeak the King's Inclinations to let the Fleet of <hi>England</hi> ſink, and the Ships rot: But Mr. <hi>Pepys</hi> has prov'd the contrary with a witneſs, and appeals to the <hi>Books</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> that are now in the <hi>Admiral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>Navy Offices.</hi> By this you may gueſs at the Sincerity of Dr. <hi>King</hi> in other particulars. King <hi>JAMES, <hi>without Taxes</hi>
               </hi> repair'd and added to our <hi>Navy,</hi> and augmented its <hi>Stores:</hi> but the Vote which declares the Senſe of the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> to be, <q>That the Commiſſion of the Admiralty ſhould not be filled with Men experienc'd in Sea-Affairs, <hi>(tho' it look like a Jeſt)</hi> was well enough calculated for the Humour of <hi>this Prince,</hi> who is willing to put the Nation under an abſolute Neceſſity of maintaining a vaſt ſtanding <hi>Army;</hi>
               </q> though a Pamphlet written and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers'd at the beginning of the laſt Seſſions, by the wiſer <hi>Williamites</hi> themſelves, called, <hi>The Intereſt or State of Parties,</hi> had ſo evidently made it out, That the Natural and only <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence</hi> of <hi>England</hi> depended upon its
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61333:12"/>
               <hi>Wooden Walls;</hi> and ſpake broadly of the Inſufficiency of the preſent <hi>Lords of the Admiralty.</hi> I ſuppoſe too, that they who occaſion'd our not making uſe laſt Summer of our Victory at Sea (which even thoſe who would fright us with the <hi>French</hi> Power, ſay was gain'd by a part only of our Fleet inferior in Number and Quality to the <hi>French,</hi> who attack'd them) and ſince have got <hi>Ruſſel</hi> diſcharg'd from being <hi>Admiral,</hi> inſtead of being rewarded with an <hi>Earldom</hi> and <hi>Garter</hi> for that Victory; which did indeed deſtroy many of the <hi>French</hi> Ships, tho' it was not <hi>the greateſt Victory that ever the Sun ſaw,</hi> (as Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> phraſed it) and yet it is the only time that we have not (by reaſon of our prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Management) come off with loſs and ſhame: I ſay, Theſe Men know how much better King <hi>William</hi> is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with <hi>Land-Forces</hi> than <hi>Tarpawlins;</hi> but how little Care ſoever has been taken of our Ships, whatever Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us to hereafter, that he may rule us more arbitrarily during his own Time, yet the Nation will find out <hi>his Deſigns,</hi> feel <hi>their own Strength,</hi> know whereon their own <hi>Safety</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, time enough to hinder <hi>his,</hi> or a <hi>French Conqueſt,</hi> tho' they will at the ſame time perceive it neceſſary to call home that <hi>Prince</hi> whoſe Claim is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſputed,</hi> and whoſe coming home upon ſuch <hi>Conceſſions</hi> as we <hi>want,</hi> and He is ready to <hi>grant,</hi> will ſwallow up all <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctions.</hi> They will e'er long per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive it neceſſary to call him home <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon ſuch <hi>Securities,</hi> even to ſecure their own <hi>Intereſts.</hi> All Remains of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Governments are at an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſince <hi>Printing</hi> has been in the World, the <hi>French</hi> and all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſo well know how vindicative of their <hi>Liberties</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have always been, that they will have but little mind to make us a <hi>Province.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have already intimated how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe it would be for the Abſolute Power of <hi>France</hi> at home, to let their Soldiers hear from the <hi>ſurviving Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> what were our <hi>Freedoms;</hi> and it would be yet much more unſafe for the <hi>French Lieutenants</hi> to agree to the Obſervation of our Laws. But I will haſten to the <hi>Norman Conqueſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before any body takes it for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that <hi>William</hi> the Firſt was a <hi>Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> I wiſh they would read the Firſt Part of the <hi>Hiſtorical Diſcourſe of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of the Government of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, written by Mr. <hi>Nathanael Bacon,</hi> and the latter-end of the third Part of Mr. <hi>Will. Prynne</hi>'s <hi>Hiſtorical Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Fundamental Liberties of Engliſh Freemen,</hi> together with all thoſe <hi>Authors</hi> theſe two Writers refer to. But I reſolved at firſt to wave ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining whether we have ever in a proper and ſtrict ſenſe been conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or no; and therefore muſt fall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly upon comparing <hi>thoſe</hi> and <hi>our Times,</hi> and the Pretences of the Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> and what the <hi>French</hi> can have upon us.</p>
            <p>I can find but one thing that has any ſhew of likeneſs with our preſent <hi>Circumſtances;</hi> and that is, <hi>Harold</hi> was an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> and had broke the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation</hi> he had formerly made to Duke <hi>William,</hi> as much as the P. of <hi>Orange</hi> has his <hi>Declaration</hi> to the <hi>People of England;</hi> and truly if any thing can facilitate a <hi>French Conqueſt,</hi> and if the Times did not exceedingly differ in other reſpects, the Breaches we have
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61333:12"/>made upon the <hi>Lineal Succeſſion,</hi> and the <hi>Impotencies, Irregularities,</hi> and <hi>Exactions</hi> of the preſent Government might make way for it: But thoſe things that made a <hi>Conquest</hi> feaſible then, and are not in our preſent Caſe, are very many.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Normans</hi> came from <hi>Norway</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> which Places were ſurchaged with People; and there was no Project ſo improbable, in which their Leaders could not eaſily engage them. The <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>Normans,</hi> and the Inhabitants of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> was the ſame. The <hi>Conqueror</hi> had many <hi>Pretences</hi> of Title: <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor's Will, the Donation of the Pope, who alſo gave him a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Banner, an <hi>Agnus</hi> of Gold, and one of the Hairs of St. <hi>Peter.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his <hi>Titles,</hi> here were ſeveral <hi>Normans</hi> within this Land, who help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him; he had been here himſelf to view our Land, and make a Party, as his own Speech intimates; the then King of <hi>France</hi> helped him in his Acqueſt: So did the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth; he likewiſe came and lived among us, and <hi>ſtipulated at his own Coronation to defend the Holy Church of God, and the Rectors of the ſame; to govern the univerſal People ſubject to him juſtly; to eſtabliſh equal Laws, and ſee them duly executed.</hi> 
               <q>Nor did be (as the Judicious <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Daniel</hi> well obſerves) ever claim any Power by Conqueſt, but as a regular Prince ſubmitted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Orders of the Kingdom, deſirous rather to have his <hi>Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Title</hi> (however weak) to make good his Succeſſion, than his <hi>Sword;</hi> and tho' the Stile of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror</hi> by the flattery of the Times was after given him, he ſhewed by all the Courſe of his Government he aſſumed it not, introducing none of thoſe Alterations (which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) by Violence, but by a mild gathering upon the diſpoſition of the State, and the Occaſions of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, and that by way of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</q> Theſe are the words of <hi>Daniel,</hi> page 36.</p>
            <p>Now I come to compare, I muſt once more repeat, That <hi>France</hi> has no occaſion to ſend forth Droves of People; and the Religion of <hi>France</hi> will make the People of <hi>England</hi> reſiſt a <hi>French Conqueſt</hi> to all Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity: And if King <hi>James</hi> would ſell his Kingdoms (as ſome ridiculouſly have ſuggeſted) the People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> would hardly be brought to make good the Bargain; and the Pope's Gift would as little influence our Minds, tho' he ſhould ſend with the Arms of <hi>France</hi> all the Reliques of <hi>Rome.</hi> We have, indeed, many <hi>French</hi> amongſt us; but I think no one Man fears they will aſſiſt their own King in ſuch an Adventure; They are ſo far from that, that they have not been (which I am ſorry to ſay) GRATEFUL to King <hi>James,</hi> who gave them <hi>Protection</hi> and <hi>Relief,</hi> when they came hither in <hi>Diſtreſs.</hi> And I have already proved, That it is not the Intereſt of any <hi>Prince</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to joyn our <hi>Three Kingdoms</hi> to the <hi>French Territories;</hi> And I believe, if the King of <hi>France</hi> ſhould promiſe <hi>to protect the</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Church of God, and the Rectors of the ſame; to govern the univerſal People ſubject to him juſtly, to eſtabliſh equal Laws, and to ſee them
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61333:13"/>duly executed;</hi> we ſhould not take his Word; nor would his own Subjects be well pleaſed. It is King <hi>William</hi> only, that is allowed to have <hi>a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion for his ſeveral Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> that may be a <hi>Synod-of-Dort-Presbyterian</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> an <hi>Epiſcopalian</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> of the <hi>Kirk</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>a downright Favourer of Popery</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as is apparent by the <hi>Lime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> Treaty, and the <hi>Pamphlet</hi> put out by the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Gentlemen, <hi>concerning the Proceedings of their late Parliament,</hi> and the <hi>Depoſiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that are before the <hi>Houſe of Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have told over our <hi>former Conqueſts</hi> ſomewhat tediouſly, and will add very little about them; however, I deſire the <hi>Reader</hi> will reflect, That the <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring Princes,</hi> becauſe they did not ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madvert how much <hi>Greatneſs</hi> conſiſted in <hi>Naval Preparations</hi> and <hi>Trade,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we had not begun to make a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure in either, never thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo much concerned, as all the <hi>Potentates</hi> of <hi>Europe</hi> will now, what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of us None of our <hi>Neighbors</hi> ever help'd <hi>Us</hi> formerly, ſome of 'em did our <hi>Invaders.</hi> Let the Reader farther reflect, that it was not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for any of our former <hi>Invaders</hi> to make ſuch a <hi>total Subverſion</hi> of all our <hi>Laws,</hi> as it will now be for the <hi>French King,</hi> and conſequently <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and Treaties more eaſily ſucceeded Battles.</hi> 
               <q>The former Alterations rather meliorated, than overthrew our Conſtitution. They bundled up and refin'd our By-Laws into National Statutes, and introduced Forms where the Methods of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſeemed leſs articulate.</q> And laſtly, Let it be conſidered, though there are great <hi>Diviſions</hi> amongſt us; <hi>ſome few</hi> for keeping the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> others for reſtoring the <hi>King,</hi> and ſeveral for ſomething that they have not yet <hi>licked into Form;</hi> yet all Perſons that make the reſpective <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of theſe <hi>Diviſions,</hi> will all of 'em joyn together to obſtruct a <hi>French Conqueſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There will be ſuch <hi>Diviſions</hi> when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Men will commit Violence upon the <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>ancient Conſtitution,</hi> and I muſt confeſs theſe <hi>Diviſions</hi> are the moſt <hi>fatal Symtom</hi> that attends our <hi>diſtemper'd State,</hi> and may, and will certainly ſubject us (though not to a <hi>French Conqueſt</hi>) to great <hi>Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities</hi> and <hi>Devaſtations,</hi> unleſs we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the <hi>King.</hi> I ſuppoſe I have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently prov'd a <hi>French Conqueſt</hi> to be neither <hi>Deſirable</hi> nor <hi>Practicable,</hi> yet God knows what infinite Miſchiefs we may have brought upon our ſelves by reviving a ſort of Quarrel which, by the Mercy of God, has been ſo long extinguiſhed. A <hi>Diſpute for Title,</hi> which has in the days of our <hi>Forefathers</hi> had ſo fatal an <hi>Effect,</hi> which has ſo <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally wounded</hi> our State, and is left bleeding in the <hi>Hiſtories</hi> of ſo many <hi>Reigns.</hi> Becauſe you ſhall not think I aggravate the Calamities, that were occaſioned by the Contention of the <hi>Two Roſes,</hi> I will only tranſribe ſome Paſſages out of <hi>Truſſel,</hi> who is a chaſt and cautelous Writer, and it cannot be ſuppoſed his Hiſtory was written to ſerve a <hi>Jacobite-Turn.</hi> Page 257. he ſays, <q>There were in the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of the Two Roſes, Fourſcore Princes of the Blood deſtroyed, and twice as many Natives ſlain, as were loſt in the Two Conqueſts
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61333:13"/>of <hi>France.</hi>
               </q> Pag. 260. he ſays, <q>In the Battle of <hi>Townton</hi> there were killed Thirty five thouſand ninety and one Engliſh-men, and of Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers One thouſand ſeven hundred forty five, beſide Two hundred and thirty ſlain the Day before at <hi>Ferry-bridge.</hi>
               </q> In his laſt Page his Words are theſe: <q>The total of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Soldiers that periſhed in theſe Civil Wars, and ſuffered Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of immature Death for taking part of the one ſide or the other, was Fourſcore thouſand nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ninety and eight Perſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides</q>
               <list>
                  <item>Kings 2.</item>
                  <item>Prince 1.</item>
                  <item>Dukes 10.</item>
                  <item>Marqueſſes 2.</item>
                  <item>Earls 21.</item>
                  <item>Viſcounts 2.</item>
                  <item>Lords 27.</item>
                  <item>Lord Prior 1.</item>
                  <item>Judge 1.</item>
                  <item>Knights 139.</item>
                  <item>Eſquires 441.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Number of the Gentry is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainly reported, and therefore <hi>Truſſel</hi> omits them, but ſays; <q>That for the moſt part they are included in the Number of private Soldiers ſet down to be ſlain, to which he ſays you muſt add the Number of Six hundred and thirty and eight, (the total of all the Perſons not therein accounted,) and then there appeareth in all to be ſlain Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore five thouſand ſix hundred twenty eight Chriſtians, and moſt of this Nation, not to be repeated (ſays the Hiſtorian) without <hi>grief,</hi> nor remembred without Depreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the like may never hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen more.</q> He concludes his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory with this Saying —</p>
            <q>Pan una Triumphis innumeris potior.</q>
            <p>The whole Hiſtory of that Quarrel ſets before us ſuch appoſite Leſſons for our Times, that I wiſh all who love <hi>England</hi> would ſeriouſly read and ponder it.</p>
            <p>It is time to draw to a Concluſion, I am not willing to prophecy the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of my <hi>Countrey,</hi> and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech God Almighty to incline our Hearts to the Things that belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our <hi>Peace;</hi> to our Peace in this World, and to our <hi>everlaſting Peace</hi> in the World to come. I beſeech God to incline the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> not to forfeit an eternal weight of Glory for a momentary Crown, which has nothing of good in it, if it is not got by the Acts of Goodneſs. God grant that he may conſider it as a more valuable Character to be a <hi>Virtuous</hi> and a <hi>Chriſtian Prince,</hi> than a <hi>Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Heroe;</hi> and God grant that he may be ſo Wiſe, that his Days may not end in <hi>Tragedy,</hi> I wiſh he would review his own <hi>Declaration</hi> and the <hi>Memorial</hi> of the States, and that he would purſue thoſe excellent Ends, for which he came, for which the States ſaid they lent their Ships, and which King <hi>James would have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd with, and is ready to comply with ſtill.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> is willing to ſecure the <hi>Liberties</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion,</hi> and had not the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates</hi> made their Quarrel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ult
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61333:14"/>by giving way to an unnatural Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition in the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and diſpoſſeſſing King <hi>James</hi> (whilſt they pretended they formed this Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy to repair the Injuries done to them by the <hi>French.</hi>)— K. <hi>JAMES,</hi> the injured King <hi>JAMES,</hi> would have checked the Growth of <hi>France,</hi> and kept <hi>Namur</hi> and <hi>Mons.</hi> He was far from a <hi>French League,</hi> and would have perform'd the part of a true <hi>Guarrantee;</hi> for either the <hi>King</hi> would have prevented <hi>France</hi> coming before them, by reminding their King of the Treaty of <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>miguen,</hi> or our Arms would have had, doubtleſs, ſucceſs when we had <hi>Juſtice</hi> on our ſide, and the <hi>Wiſhes</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> of all <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh-men</hi> joyned with the underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of our <hi>rightful indiſputed King.</hi> How far he was from a <hi>French League,</hi> how unwilling to think ill of the Pr. of <hi>Orange,</hi> and how unwilling to be <hi>too much</hi> beholding to <hi>France,</hi> his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief of all the Advices of <hi>d'Avaux,</hi> and of many of his Friends, his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>Bonrepos,</hi> and his refuſal to the laſt of any <hi>French Aſſiſtance</hi> ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently witneſs; and as much as he has been beholding to <hi>France</hi> during his Troubles, I am ſatisfied that even in his <hi>exil'd State</hi> he thinks himſelf (as King of <hi>England</hi>) ſo naturally the <hi>Arbiter of Europe,</hi> that he will me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate, as ſoon as his Affairs a little more recover his <hi>Figure</hi> a reaſonable Peace for it. But the KING needs not much ſolicite it, for I am ſatisfy'd the King of <hi>France</hi> is willing to come into ſuch a Peace, upon Condition that the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Reſtauration</hi> may be one of the Terms of it, and that he will not be brought to make Peace upon any other Terms; ſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Reſtauration of King JAMES</hi> would give a happy Iſſue to the Troubles of <hi>Europe,</hi> and <hi>our own,</hi> which our Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience (after all the Blood and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſpilt and ſpent to humble <hi>France</hi>) may ſhew us will be the only Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſave us from the <hi>Power</hi> we have ſo much envy'd; and this we may learn from King <hi>William</hi>'s own Spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to theſe two laſt Seſſions of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; for he does not only make the obtaining an <hi>Honourable Peace</hi> from <hi>France</hi> to the <hi>Confederates</hi> (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of our <hi>Conqueſt of France</hi>) the Bounds of his Hopes in this War, but allows the Growth of <hi>France</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this War ſo much, as to increaſe his Stile from the <hi>Great <hi>Power of France,</hi>
               </hi> (which were the words of his Speech <hi>Michaelmas</hi> was Twelve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>months) to the <hi>Exceſſive <hi>Power of France,</hi>
               </hi> in his Speech of the laſt Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. This very Conſideration ſhould move us. But farther.</p>
            <p>Into what Shambles are all the Parts of <hi>Flanders</hi> the <hi>Rhine, Catalonia,</hi> and <hi>Piedmont</hi> turn'd? What <hi>Slaughter-Houſes</hi> may be erected in the unhappy Iſle of <hi>Britain?</hi> Unhappy, becauſe ſhe will blind her ſelf againſt her own <hi>true Intereſt</hi> and <hi>only Cure.</hi> Our <hi>Taxes</hi> grow heavy, but we have pay'd our Blood, but we muſt pour it out yet more plentifully, before this Reckoning is over; if we will not return to our <hi>Wits</hi> and our <hi>Duty, Civil Diſtractions</hi> will overtake us; <hi>Foreigners</hi> both on the one and the other ſide will be poured in upon us, and we ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the <hi>Cock-Pit</hi> of the World; and though all the <hi>Jacobites</hi> abhor a <hi>French Conqueſt,</hi> and ſo does the <hi>King</hi> too,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61333:14"/>yet if the Nation will not come to ſuch a Temper as to reſtore him without <hi>their Help,</hi> the KING's Friends cannot be blamed for being willing to admit of ſuch a moderate Number of <hi>French,</hi> or any other For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as may be neceſſary to cover <hi>Them,</hi> when they come to him, till they get together, and as may give them <hi>Opportunity</hi> to riſe. We had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Nation looked ſo directly towards <hi>Him,</hi> as that there ſhould be no occaſion for <hi>One Man</hi> in Arms to come with Him. <hi>We</hi> had rather, <hi>He</hi> had much rather, nay the <hi>King of France</hi> declares, HE had rather his <hi>Reſtauration</hi> ſhould be wholly owing to his own <hi>Subjects.</hi> We will never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree that he ſhould bring ſuch a Force as may give any the leaſt juſt Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, that either <hi>He</hi> or <hi>France</hi> deſign to Conquer; and he is perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to come in that manner that ſhall be agreed to by ſuch Friends of his, as the World muſt allow to be Men of Honour, regardful of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Rights, and of the Proteſtant Religion. With ſuch Men he will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt the <hi>Manner</hi> and <hi>Time</hi> of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. They will ſee, that his coming ſhall be ſafe to all thoſe <hi>dear Concerns</hi> for which we have ſo often ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled; and the <hi>Meaſures</hi> and <hi>Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentions</hi> ſuch, as that they may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to God and Men their engaging in his Quarrel.</p>
            <p>Can any Man of Senſe believe that the Earl of <hi>Middleton;</hi> who could never during his whole Miniſtry be drawn into any one irregular ſtep, would go over upon any other Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand? That Great Man is known to underſtand his Duty to his <hi>Countrey</hi> as well as his <hi>Prince,</hi> and thinks he ought at the ſame time to be the <hi>Miniſter</hi> of <hi>both,</hi> and his Affection and Firmneſs to <hi>Proteſtancy</hi> was never once ſuſpected: He will neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray <hi>our</hi> Laws, nor his <hi>own</hi> Religion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; nor will he, to do the King <hi>but Juſtice,</hi> be tempted to either; for all that we have miſlik'd in the <hi>King's Meaſures</hi> abroad, has proceeded from <hi>Miſr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>preſentations</hi> from hence; and my Lord <hi>Middleton</hi> is ſo fraughted with the genuine Intereſt as well as Senſe of theſe Nations that the moſt inveterate of our Enemies will have hereafter no Opportunities to clamor and exaſperate. This is a Truth which in a ſhort time will want no <hi>Vouchers.</hi> The future Acts of <hi>State</hi> that come from that Court will prove he has diſcourſed many of the <hi>Leading</hi> Men, and compromiſed the <hi>Grievances of all Parties.</hi> And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſome of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Miniſters have declared what great Expectations they have from the Quarrels at St. <hi>Germains,</hi> I can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them they will be deceived in their Hopes; for there is ſo good an Underſtanding between my Lord <hi>Middleton</hi> and thoſe who had before entire Credit with the King, that they don't only perſonally agree, but concur in Sentiments relating to the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Affairs; which is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull Evidence that what we miſliked there cannot be charged upon the Diſpoſition of the King, nor upon the depraved Tempers of thoſe about him (as even ſome of his Friends were apt to ſuſpect) but proceeded meerly from their want of a True State of theſe Nations, and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61333:15"/>of what would ſatisfie us, till the Eart of <hi>Middleton</hi> went thither Every day will make this Truth plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than other.</p>
            <p>I cannot but wiſh, that all Men would ſo avowedly own their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, would ſo willingly ſit down under our Ancient, Legal, Limited, and Hereditary <hi>Monarchy,</hi> would ſo openly tell their D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſatisfactions, and what they think Proportionate Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curities, ſo fairly ſtate the Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces between the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> ſo unanimouſly expreſs their Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs to Re-eſtabliſh the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>Natural Frame</hi> of our <hi>Government,</hi> that it might be adviſable that we might adviſe him wholly to depend upon his <hi>Britiſh</hi> Subjects. I like neither <hi>French,</hi> nor <hi>Dutch,</hi> nor <hi>Iriſh</hi> upon our Iſland, though I cannot be afraid of any ſuch Numbers of either, or all, as will be much out-numbred by thoſe of our <hi>Fellow-Subjects</hi> and <hi>Fellow Iſlanders,</hi> who reſolve to repair to the <hi>King</hi> as ſoon as he is landed. Oh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that we would recant our <hi>Miſtakes!</hi> that we would repent of our <hi>Folly!</hi> that we would yet let our <hi>Moderation,</hi> our Civil and Chriſtian Moderation, be known unto all Men! Oh! that a nice Security for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as the <hi>National Church</hi> (and <hi>beſt Church</hi> too, as I think) as nice a Security for our (<hi>Engliſh Libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ties,</hi> and <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> were our only Aims! that <hi>Party</hi> and <hi>Picque Faction</hi> and <hi>Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fears</hi> and <hi>Fancies,</hi> did not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inate neither on the, One nor the Other Party! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at the <hi>Ends,</hi> and not the <hi>Forms</hi> of Things were what we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord that our Afflictions would make us Wiſe! then the King would as little <hi>need</hi> as he <hi>wiſhes</hi> to bring any <hi>Foreign Force.</hi> See you any end of your Troubles? Is your <hi>Deliverer</hi> a fit Inſtrument for ſo great a Work? Do his <hi>Meaſures</hi> hold any reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance with <hi>his</hi> and <hi>your Pretences?</hi> Are his miniſters, <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r—n.</hi> and <hi>Not—m, Tr—r, Roch—r,</hi> and <hi>Sey—r, Ren—augh, G—y, Bla—t,</hi> and Convert-reconvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Sund—d,</hi> (behind the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;) together with his Creature <hi>Br—n,</hi> (that indefatigable Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary to all Turns, and to the <hi>High Commiſſion Court,</hi> that Aſſiſtant to the ſour <hi>Popiſh Biſhops, ready Evidence,</hi> and <hi>induſtrious Informer;</hi>) and <hi>Con—by,</hi> of whoſe Merits in <hi>Ireland</hi> the Parliament here took ſo much notice, that he is ſince taken into the Privy Council of <hi>England,</hi> for his undoubted Integrity, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard-of Abilities; with the long Roll of ſuch ſort of Men, (though his ſinking Game has forc'd him to call ſome lately into his Councils, who have not <hi>yet</hi> loſt their Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the People) fit <hi>Guardians</hi> for that <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> which you ſo juſtly value? Think ſeriouſly, Ought the People of <hi>England</hi> to truſt theſe Men, or have they reaſon to truſt one another, even in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of that <hi>Maſter</hi> they pretend to ſerve? Awaken out of your Dreams; Get rid of your Phantaſins; Conſider as Men; Act as Lovers of your Country; Reſcue your Rights; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore you KING, who will confirm thoſe Rights with ſolid Securities; Do your own Work, that After Ages may pity your Miſtakes, and give
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61333:15"/>Allowance for your Reſentment; and that You and your Childrens Children may be happy. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the God of <hi>Order,</hi> That He will produce it out of our <hi>Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions;</hi> That the <hi>King</hi> may have what is due to <hi>Him,</hi> and that <hi>we</hi> may have what is <hi>as much</hi> due to <hi>us;</hi> and that the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>People</hi> may both praiſe the Almighty for his Mercies to this Land, this miſerable and ſinful Land.</p>
            <p>Let the Senſe of our Miſeries, our Faults, and our Duty, ſtir us up. Let the ſad Example of former Times exhort us. Let us, I ſay, CALL HOME THE KING, with an exact Security to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as the <hi>National Church,</hi> and with ſuch ſolid Securities for our Liberties, as may make all other <hi>Religions <hi>harmleſs Opinions,</hi>
               </hi> tho' we allow them a fair and impartial <hi>Liberty;</hi> And yet let us not ſo ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the Crown, that it will not be able to protect us from our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and one another; Let us not ſay, That the hands of the Nation are bound, and that it <hi>cannot</hi> call home the King; For if all thoſe who plainly ſee that we ſhall be <hi>undone</hi> under this <hi>Uſurpation;</hi> and likewiſe that it is impoſſible <hi>this Government</hi> ſhould ſtand (though it ſhills about now it is in an ill taking) would up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Terms joyn with thoſe who are for the <hi>Reſtauration of King James,</hi> as well in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, as all over the Nation, from the ſad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect they have of the Ruin of that <hi>Liberty</hi> (the miſtaken <hi>Jealouſie</hi> and <hi>Care</hi> of which, was the <hi>only Motive</hi> that hurry'd them into what they did) all the Force the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> has would ſoon diſſolve, and he muſt be glad to return again, and ſpend all his time at the <hi>Loo</hi> (which our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Money</hi> is making ſo fine a Retreat) and at the <hi>Hague;</hi> which is the very worſt, I call God to witneſs, that I ever wiſhed him.</p>
            <p>I am conſcious I have not, in all the parts of this Diſcourſe, written with that brevity, which I deſign'd at the beginning of it, and may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be guilty of ſome <hi>Redundancies, Tautologies,</hi> and <hi>Repetitions,</hi> as well in other places, as I have in my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks</hi> upon our <hi>former Invaſions</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted ſome paſſages, which croſſed my way, though they were rather applicable to our preſent times, than ſutable to the Thread of my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. When a Man writes Things of this Nature, he is willing to be rid of them as faſt as they are finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though they may not be ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect; and notwithſtanding the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks (for whoſe: either <hi>praiſe</hi> or <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion</hi> I never ſcribble) may find ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Faults with them, I have ſet down Things, as I am perſwaded in my own Mind, and as I have heard them diſcourſed by the conſiderable and influencing <hi>Jacobites</hi> of the ſeveral Denominations; though I muſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for my unskilful and careleſs cloathing and ranging their Thoughts; I hope I have generally kept in ſight of my Text; and I ſuppoſe alſo have upon the whole made good what I undertook to prove, <hi>viz.</hi> That a <hi>French Conqueſt is neither deſirable nor practicable.</hi> If it is unſutable to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61333:16"/>
               <hi>Intereſts</hi> and <hi>Inclinations</hi> of the ſeveral ſorts of <hi>Jacobites,</hi> and contrary to the <hi>King's Inclinations,</hi> and the Intereſts of all our Neighbours; and the very <hi>Attempt</hi> of it, either for himſelf, or King <hi>James,</hi> contrary to the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Intereſt; if the Condition and Circumſtances of the <hi>French Power</hi> to make a <hi>Conqueſt</hi> and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in ſuch an Experiment, and that of our former <hi>Invaders</hi> and the State of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Affairs <hi>now</hi> and what they were <hi>then,</hi> ſo very much differ; I think we may infer, That a <hi>French Conqueſt is neither deſirable nor practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable;</hi> and that it is as weak to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>France</hi> can or will <hi>conquer</hi> us, as it is to believe <hi>we ſhall ſack Paris,</hi> and <hi>conquer France,</hi> with the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> at the Head of the <hi>Britiſh Forces,</hi> who we ſee with <hi>Them,</hi> and all the <hi>Confederate-ſtrength,</hi> has ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently paſs'd his Campaigns in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61333:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
